{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man appointed George Creel to head the Committee on Public Information, a propaganda\nmachine. He attacked those who “poured the poison of disloyalty” in a State of the Union address, but\nwas unable to get a press-censorship clause in the Espionage Act. For ten points, name this President who\nreneged on a campaign promise to “keep us out of the War” by committing American forces to World\nWar I.",
      "answer": [
        "Woodrow Wilson",
        "Wilson"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this novel, a “resurrection man” emerges from the mists in front of a mail coach. John Barsad\nplants evidence on a man who is a lookalike of a drunken lawyer; that man ends this novel by saying “it\nis a far, far better rest that I go to than I have ever known” at the guillotine. French nobleman Marquis\nSt. Evremonde is the uncle of Charles Darnay in, for ten points, what novel by Charles Dickens set during\nthe French Revolution?",
      "answer": "A Tale of Two Cities"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, General Howe lost many of his officers, including John Pitcairn. According to\nlegend, someone during this battle gave the order “Don’t shoot until you see the whites of their eyes.”\nJoseph Warren was killed at, for ten points, what Revolutionary War battle outside Boston that, despite\nits name, mostly took place on Breed’s Hill?",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Bunker Hill",
        "Bunker Hill"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person’s life savings were swindled by two men who claimed to have gold from a distant relative.\nThis spy for the Union during the Raid on Combahee Ferry had biographies written by Sarah Hopkins\nBradford, which described her navigating a network of tunnels and safehouses. For ten points, name this\nabolitionist who escorted slaves as they escaped on the Underground Railroad.",
      "answer": [
        "Harriet Tubman",
        "Tubman"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure was guarded by a group of horsemen called the Celeres, and he may be associated with\nthe war god Quirinus because of his disappearance near the Quirinal Hill. He proclaimed “so perish every\none hereafter that will leap over my wall” while killing his brother after they debated the meaning of the\nnumber of birds flying around their heads. For ten points, name this brother of Remus, the first king of\nthe Romans.",
      "answer": "Romulus"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man “smelt a rat in Philadelphia” and refused to attend the Constitutional Convention. In\none speech, he said “Caesar had his Brutus, Charles his Cromwell” to the House of Burgesses over his\nopposition to the Stamp Act, and his most famous speech occurred at St. John’s Church in a debate on\nsending troops during the American Revolution. For ten points, name this American founding father who\nproclaimed “Give me liberty or give me death!\"",
      "answer": [
        "Patrick Henry",
        "Henry"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Yaghan people are native to this island chain. Its largest city of Ushuaia [oosh-WHY-uh] was\nestablished as a penal colony and is served by the End of the World Train. The Drake Passage lies south\nof this island chain, and far fewer ships rounded its Cape Horn after the opening of the Panama Canal.\nFor ten points, name this archipelago shared between Chile and Argentina on the southern tip of South\nAmerica, whose Spanish name translates as “land of fire.”",
      "answer": "Tierra del Fuego"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2003, a copy of this painting was covered by a blue curtain while Colin Powell addressed the United\nNations. On the left side of this painting, a bull stands over a woman who is holding her dead child. An\neye-shaped light bulb explodes in this painting above an impaled, screaming horse. For ten points, name\nthis painting inspired by the bombing of the title Basque town, a massive painting by Pablo Picasso.",
      "answer": "Guernica"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man directed a 2005 film where he played Fred Friendly, a colleague of Edward Murrow, as well\nas a 2014 film about the recovery of art in Nazi Germany. This director of Good Night and Good Luck\nand The Monuments Men operates a project to monitor Sudanese war crimes via satellite imagery. For\nten points, name this American actor who starred as Daniel Ocean in the Ocean’s 11 trilogy and with\nSandra Bullock in 2013’s Gravity.",
      "answer": [
        "George Clooney",
        "Clooney"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler attempted to establish the Kingdom of Livonia as a vassal state, and this ruler established\nhis country’s first printing press at Kitai-gorod. This ruler conquered Kazan and Astrakhan, and he\nestablished a secret police force known as the Oprichniki. Feodor I succeeded this ruler after he killed his\neldest son in a fit of rage, eventually leading to the Time of Troubles. For ten points, name this first Tsar\nof Russia whose epithet notes his power, not his cruelty.",
      "answer": [
        "Ivan IV of Russia",
        "Ivan IV",
        "Ivan the Terrible",
        "Ivan Grozny"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) The War of Jenkins’ Ear was part of what larger conflict over succession to a European\nthrone?",
      "answer": [
        "War of the Austrian Succession",
        "Austrian"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The price elasticity of this quantity should always be negative, but Veblen goods violate that theory.\nJohn Maynard Keynes argued that, in recessions, the aggregate of this quantity should be bolstered by\ngovernment spending. During the Irish Potato Famine, this quantity rose for potatoes even as their price\nrose, as people could no longer afford luxuries like meat. For ten points, name this economic quantity\nthat, in competitive markets, should reach equilibrium with supply.",
        "answer": "demand"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A demand shock may be triggered by these events, such as one passed by President Bush in 2001\nand made permanent for most Americans in wake of the 2012 fiscal cliff.",
        "answer": [
          "tax cuts",
          "tax cut"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The inefficient Trabant was built in this former country. It used distinctive Ampelm¨annchen crosswalk\nsymbols that are now enjoyed as its modern residents experience “Ostalgie.” Its residents were once spied\non by the Markus Wolf-led Stasi, which revealed its records after reunification in 1990. For ten points,\nname this former Soviet-zone country with capital Berlin.",
        "answer": [
          "East Germany",
          "German Democratic Republic",
          "GDR",
          "Deutsche Demokratische Republik",
          "DDR"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Oder-Neisse Line provided the border between East Germany and what other country?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Poland",
          "Poland"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, paratroopers captured bridges on the River Orne and Saint-M`ere-Eglise. The First ´\nUS Army Group participated in Operation Quicksilver prior to this campaign, and was commanded by\nGeneral Patton. The Canadians were supposed to capture Caen during this operation, and the Americans\nwere assigned to Fortress Cherbourg, part of the Atlantic Wall. For ten points, name this operation, an\nAllied landing on five beaches in Northern France.",
        "answer": [
          "Operation Overlord",
          "Overlord",
          "D-Day",
          "Battle of Normandy",
          "Normandy"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Operation Dragoon, landings after Operation Overlord in the south of France, targeted Toulon\nand this other Mediterranean port, now the second largest French city.",
        "answer": "Marseilles"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This object was excommunicated by Calixtus III, who believed it boded evil for the defenders of\nBelgrade. Mark Twain said that this object and he were “two unaccountable freaks” and claimed that he\nwould “go out with it,” a prediction that came true when he died in 1910. The Giotto Probe flew through\nthe coma of this object in 1986, which will be visible again in 2061. For ten points, name this comet that\napproaches Earth roughly every 76 years.",
        "answer": [
          "Halley’s comet",
          "Halley",
          "1P/Halley"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1910, Earth passed through this feature of Halley’s comet, leading some to buy gas masks in\nfear that Earth’s atmosphere would be poisoned.",
        "answer": "the tail"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Kate Altman’s testimony of this event was discredited after one lawyer asked her to repeat her version\nmultiple times. Frances Perkins was sent to investigate this event, for which Max Blanck and Isaac Harris\nstood trial for locking exit doors from the outside, leading to the deaths of 146 workers. For ten points,\nname this 1911 disaster in a New York garment factory.",
        "answer": [
          "Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire",
          "Triangle Shirtwaist"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the disaster, this New York political machine, then led by Al Smith, supported reforms.",
        "answer": [
          "Tammany Hall",
          "Tammany"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s controversial STRESS program was ended by Mayor Coleman Young. During the 12th\nStreet Riot, Lyndon B. Johnson sent the 101st Airborne to this city, where they provided support for\nGeorge Romney’s National Guard. Its wealthier suburbs are separated from this city’s poorer areas by 8\nMile Road, and this city’s 1943 Race Riots erupted over tensions caused by high paying automotive jobs.\nFor ten points, name this largest city in Michigan.",
        "answer": "Detroit"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This rhyming phrase describes the racially motivated phenomenon of migration to the suburbs,\nas prominently seen in 1960s Detroit.",
        "answer": "White Flight"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man fought during the Second Baron’s War against Simon de Montfort, who he killed at the\nBattle of Evesham. This monarch issued the Edict of Expulsion, which expelled all Jews from England.\nHe invaded Scotland, winning the Battle of Falkirk against the forces of William Wallace. For ten points,\nname this English King given the name “Longshanks” because of his height.",
        "answer": "Edward I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Edward I’s father Henry III was forced by the barons to agree to the Provisions of Oxford, which\nheavily influenced this later document that was signed by John I at Runnymede.",
        "answer": "Magna Carta"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A portion of this structure was built in the contested Ordos region. The early heqin [huh-CHEEN]\nsystem allowed the Xiongnu [tchee-ONG-noo] to rule the area north of this structure. The Jiayu Pass\nserves as the end of one section of this structure built by the Ming dynasty to defend against Mongol\nattacks. For ten points, name this massive series of Chinese defensive fortifications.",
        "answer": [
          "Great Wall of China",
          "Great Wall"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The deal with the Xiongnu occurred under the ruler of this dynasty. The history of this dynasty,\nwhich also names China’s largest ethnic group, was chronicled by Sima Qian [su-mah chee-en].",
        "answer": [
          "Han Dynasty",
          "Han"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "THE U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The other federal legislative body, with two members per state?",
          "answer": "Senate"
        },
        {
          "question": "The current number of State Representatives?",
          "answer": "435"
        },
        {
          "question": "The article of the Constitution providing for the legislature, including the House?",
          "answer": [
            "Article 1",
            "1"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The process of accusing a federal official of wrongdoing, which only the House can begin?",
          "answer": "impeachment"
        },
        {
          "question": "The title given to the presiding officer?",
          "answer": [
            "Speaker of the House",
            "Speaker"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The Ohio representative who announced his resignation from that post in 2015?",
          "answer": [
            "John Boehner",
            "Boehner"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The former holder of that position whose “Contract with America” helped win Republicans the House\nin 1994?",
          "answer": [
            "Newt Gingrich",
            "Gingrich"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The future Attorney General who proposed the Virginia Plan, foreshadowed the House, at the\nConstitutional Convention?",
          "answer": [
            "Edmund Randolph",
            "Randolph"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Considering the United States House of Representatives, who or what is..."
    },
    {
      "category": "GERMAN CULTURE",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The once-divided German capital city?",
          "answer": "Berlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Christian holiday celebrated with street markets called Weihnachtsmarkt [VYE-nakts-markt]\nand advent calendars?",
          "answer": [
            "Christmas",
            "Christmas Eve",
            "Christmas Day"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The sibling storytellers of fairy tales like Hansel and Gretel?",
          "answer": [
            "Brothers Grimm",
            "Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm",
            "Grimm"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The highway system whose efficiency and lack of speed limits inspired President Eisenhower?",
          "answer": "Autobahn"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Bavarian capital city whose beer halls sponsor the annual Oktoberfest?",
          "answer": "Munich"
        },
        {
          "question": "The NBA MVP who has played 17 seasons for the Dallas Mavericks?",
          "answer": [
            "Dirk Nowitzki",
            "Nowitzki"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The founder of the Bayreuth [bye-ROYT] opera house, where his Ring Cycle is annually performed?",
          "answer": [
            "Richard Wagner",
            "Wagner"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The German art and architecture school founded by Walter Gropius?",
          "answer": "Bauhaus"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "What is..."
    },
    {
      "category": "MIDDLE EASTERN CONFLICT AND PROTEST",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Had a 2013 coup d’etat remove Mohamed Morsi from power in Cairo?",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Has lost territory to ISIS but is still led from Baghdad?",
          "answer": "Iraq"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attacked the Hamas-ruled Gaza Strip to its west in 2014?",
          "answer": "Israel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Signed the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action, limiting its nuclear production capabilities in\nexchange for relaxed sanctions?",
          "answer": "Iran"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is torn by civil fighting in and around Aleppo?",
          "answer": "Syria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the base of the militant group Hezbollah?",
          "answer": "Lebanon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was invaded by Saddam Hussein in 1990, triggering the first Persian Gulf War?",
          "answer": "Kuwait"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of the 2000 USS Cole bombing in a port on the Arabian Peninsula?",
          "answer": "Yemen"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which Middle Eastern country..."
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a letter to John Holmes, Thomas Jefferson commented that this law had “awakened\nand filled me with terror.” James Tallmadge unsuccessfully proposed that this law make (20 pts) ",
        "children of slaves free after reaching 25 years old. It was overturned by the (10 pts) ",
        "Kansas-Nebraska Act and ruled unconstitutional in Dred Scott v. Sanford. For ten points, name this 1820\ncompromise that banned slavery in certain regions of the Louisiana Purchase, except in a namesake state."
      ],
      "answer": "Missouri Compromise"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was thought to be aboard a plane carrying the Bolivian president in 2013, but\nhe had not left Sheremetyevo Airport since arriving there from Hong Kong. This former\nemployee of (20 pts) ",
        "Booz Allen Hamilton was attempting to avoid extradition to the U.S. after\nleaking sensitive (10 pts) ",
        "documents to Glenn Greenwald. For ten points, name this man who in June 2013\nrevealed the extent of U.S. government surveillance programs such as PRISM."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Edward Joseph Snowden",
        "Snowden"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) James Monroe vouched for this man’s U.S. citizenship, freeing him from French prison.\nHe was sued for libel after writing a response to Edmund Burke’s Reflections on the (20 pts) ",
        "Revolution in France, and he criticized organized religion and the divinity of the Bible\nwhile advocating for the rise of deism in The (10 pts) ",
        "Age of Reason. The absurdity of an island\nruling a continent was observed by, for ten points, what early American revolutionary thinker in his 1776\npamphlet Common Sense?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Thomas Paine",
        "Paine"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This adjective names a white supremacist “Council of Citizens” led by Earl Holt. Brent\nBozell ghostwrote a book for Arizona Senator Barry Goldwater about The Conscience of\nthis type of person. The Canadian Alliance (20 pts) ",
        "merged with another party to form the\nCanadian political party of this name, which was, until October 2015, led by Stephen (10 pts) ",
        "Harper. Traditional cultural institutions are supported by, for ten points, what political philosophy that\ndescribes the American Republican Party, contrasted with “liberalism”?"
      ],
      "answer": "conservative"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Livy claims that one participant in this conflict used heated vinegar to cross a blocked\nmountain pass. Quintus Fabius was nicknamed “the delayer” during this conflict for refusing\nto engage in battle. One side in this conflict lost at (20 pts) ",
        "Lake Trasimene [trah-sih-meh-nee]\nbut later won the decisive victory on the plains of Zama under Scipio [SKIP-ee-oh],\ncounteracting a devastating loss at Cannae [CANN-aye]. The (10 pts) ",
        "Alps were traversed by\nHannibal during, for ten points, what second of a series of conflicts between Rome and Carthage?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "2nd Punic War",
        "2nd Punic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one work set in this country, the title character sings “All alba vincero!” or “At\ndawn, I will win!” In another work set in this country, a woman interrupts a performance\nof The Red Detachment of Women. The aria (20 pts) ",
        "“Nessun dorma” is sung by Prince Calaf\nin this setting of Giacomo Puccini’s (10 pts) ",
        "Turandot. John Adams composed an opera about a 1972\nPresidential visit to, for ten points, what country where Richard Nixon met Mao Zedong?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "People’s Republic of China",
        "China"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A second investigation of this event was chaired by Ramsey Clark. The most complete\nrecording of this event was sold to Life Magazine for $150,000 by Abraham (20 pts) ",
        "Zapruder.\nJohn Connally was seriously wounded during this event, which was performed from the\nsixth floor of the (10 pts) ",
        "Texas School Book Depository. Jack Ruby killed the perpetrator of this event\nbefore he could stand trial. For ten points, name this event in which Lee Harvey Oswald shot the 35th\npresident of the United States."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "assassination of John Fitzgerald Kennedy",
        "assassination of JFK",
        "assassination of J Kennedy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city’s empire defeated Ercole d’Este to conquer Commachio and defeated a rival in\nthe War of Chioggia. It was targeted by the League of (20 pts) ",
        "Cambrai, founded by its nemesis\nJulius II. Its Arsenale was said to be able to produce one (10 pts) ",
        "warship a day. A fleet from this\ncity was led by Enrico Dandolo in the Fourth Crusade and sacked Constantinople. For ten points, name\nthis “Most Serene Republic” which was ruled by doges."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Most Serene Republic of Venice",
        "Venice"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) According to Tarikh al-Sudan, this empire’s last ruler was Mahmud IV, whose\ndefeat at the Battle of Djenne caused its collapse. The ton-tigi, or “quiver-masters,”\nadvised this empire’s rulers at its (20 pts) ",
        "Gbara legislature. Its constitution, the\nKouroukan Fouga, was established after its first ruler won the Battle of Kirina. This\nempire’s most famous ruler (10 pts) ",
        "caused inflation by spending tons of gold on his way to Mecca.\nFor ten points, name this West African empire led by Sundieta Keita and Mansa Musa."
      ],
      "answer": "Mali Empire"
    }
  ]
}